our next topic is fish oil more
specifically what I mean here is DHA and
EPA DHA is accumulated in the brain in
fact it's about 10% of your brain or so
so makes a lot of sense that this one's
going to be pretty important it's
critical for everything from
neurological function to injury risk
metabolic rate uh prevention of neurod
degeneration aging and brain health and
Alzheimer's dementia so on and so forth
incredibly important to actual structure
EPA is a little bit different it's
mainly involved in vascular function
inflammation oxygen delivery uh nutrient
delivery to the brain and so on and so
forth right so these are typically tied
together so I'm not going to really
differentiate them as most Omega-3s come
with both EPA and DHA now while I said
earlier that creatine is by far the most
studied sport supplement because it is
Omega-3s are by far the most studied
regarding traumatic brain injury there
are dozens and dozens of studies
systematic reviews randomized control
trials on Omega-3s and brain related
injuries and various head traumas
however you might be surprised to know
I'm not aware of any direct evidence of
Omega-3s and TB so this is a great
example of me saying hey look there's
still a lot of good tangential or
indirect evidence here so much I feel
like it's overwhelming but not
necessarily that much directly on tbis
for the reasons we described earlier
they're just hard studies to carry out
in general what you're going to see is
frankly they work they work for both pre
and post impacts
theoe is technically three here and you
generally see main effects and benefits
from cerebral profusion so this is
getting that blood and oxygen and and
flow of nutrients in and out of the
brain remember the primary cause of
injury there is that structural that
tissue and that axon shearing that that
kind of ripping apart and so what that
does is cause that Cascade
of secondary insults that mismatch the
blood flow and the metabolic demand we
talked about that earlier Omega-3s land
right on that problem uh for Solutions
and the reason is it helps dramatically
with what's called arterial pliability
and compliance and so when we're having
issues getting blood in the arteries can
either be broke or damaged or stiff and
Omega-3s really help it become more
pliable and open and close more
effectively is one way to think about
about it it's also why you see so much
evidence in research on Omega thees for
heart health and blood pressure and so
on and so forth has the same effect
essentially in the brain other thing it
does that's a huge benefit outside of
that cerebral profusion is it modulates
inflammation post injury by regulating
that Ross reactive auction species it
interacts with all kinds of cyto kindes
like interlukin 1 and tnf Alpha if
you're familiar with those if not don't
worry about it um even actually there's
one in particular called nfkb that brain
folks will know exactly what I'm talking
about here um this actually functionally
it affects a gene expression of a bunch
of inflammatory things so it kind of
cuts off inflammation at the genetic
level so lots of ways that it has an
impact to give you a couple specific
examples one of the most common issues
associated with
TBI long-term is called atrophy of the
hippocampus now that's associated in one
of the areas that's mainly responsible
for learning in memory and we know that
those are problems right we know that
higher Omega-3 intake is associated with
a bigger hippocampal volume right so we
have cross-sectional studies here
longitudinal ones that suggest again
people that consume more tend to have a
larger hippocampus and we also see a
significant increase in these areas at
the dosage of about 2.2 gram per day
okay 2.2 grams of fish per day
associated with bigger hippocampus
therefore potential to improve or
enhance our learning in memory similar
things have been done with memory
specifically
uh in fact one study looked at I think
it was a combination of 900 Mig of EPA
plus 260 Mig of DHA and that resulted in
greater accuracy and speed of recall
tasks so mental recall memory EPA in
general is often really associated with
cognitive function and the DHA is
associated with acdal injuries um works
on a thing called neurofilament light or
NFL and that's actually been
specifically shown in college football
players I believe again at that two G
per day dosage of
DHA so in general to get to the end here
the dosage for brain related injuries is
somewhere between 2 to four grams per
day though there's really little risk
the only adverse issue you're going to
typically have here is potentially some
loose
stool again there's not that much
evidence of it but if you have a you
consume a bunch of oil that can kind of
run through you a little bit probably
not going to see much happen there very
often the timing of it doesn't matter
that much you can you would certainly
want to be taking it before the injury
as well as after the injury and the
timing of the day is honestly totally
irrelevant and so pretty easy pretty
fast one to go through very effective I
personally will be totally honest I take
a lot more than four grams for other
benefits but very fairly the available
evidence on not necessarily directly TBI
rcts but the other Associated areas of
brain health and injury and damage
pretty consistently show the effect
happen at about two or so grams and
studies that have looked at higher
dosages don't see any additional benefit
so I think it's very fair to say two
grams a day or so is the effective dose
and more than that may not give you
additional benefit what's that look like
from food another example where vegans
and
vegetarians really should honestly
strongly consider supplementation here
we're going to get fish oil from fish
pretty obviously right salmon Herring
sardines mackerels trout are generally
the most highest concentration ones
salmon being the most obvious example
that's got about two grams of fish oil
per 100 grams of cooked meat again that'
be 3 and a half ounces or so which is
not an outrageous dosage at all
unfortunately the standard American diet
is typically about 100 milligrams of
Omega-3s per day and we need you to get
to to two all right so you're going to
have to up your anti it's totally
possible but most people just don't do
enough of it this is a really important
one to go after I know I just covered
information but I want to also highlight
the fact you can check what I mean by
that is unlike creatine where it's going
to be really hard to measure your
creatine monohydrate especially in your
brain levels you as a preventative
strategy should look at your omega-3
index and identify whether you have
problems because there's a lot of
evidence that suggest if you go into a
brain injury with the better 3 the brain
injury will be less significant so our
starting place here is to actually not
go into the injury with a problem I
mention this but I'll be more clear the
omega-3 index is not a perfect way to
measure it but it is an effective blood
test you can get done and what that's
going to effectively tell you is the
percentage of EPA and DHA that's in the
membrane of your red blood cells and
there's been a handful of studies on
this that are quite impressive my
opinion um studies on football players
and even uh a basketball players have
found that the mass majority of them
have an omega-3 index of less than 5%
optimal is like 8 to 10 maybe even 12
the overwhelming majority of these
athletes are less than five in fact I
think the studies I'm thinking of right
now uh the two kind of combined
basically none of the athletes had
higher than 7% again 8 to 12 is what
we're looking for in fact the reason
we're doing that is because there's been
known and shown documented cognitive
benefits at 10% plus even as low as 8%
Plus so in these studies no athletes are
there in fact most of the over 50% of
the athletes in these studies had an
omega-3 index of less than 4% so it is
really really really common in our
athletes to see omega-3 status being
really
insufficient and the same thing has
happened in the general population so
you can 100% achieve enough for brain
health through food if you'd like you
just need to make a considered effort
for it and you can see and and go back
to hear the dosages or can use
supplements or a combination but you
absolutely want to make sure that you're
doing this
prophylactically as well as if you do
experience an injury getting right on
the supplementation as quickly as you
can if you enjoyed this clip you can
watch the full episode by clicking here